This is a big deal. This is going to
change the way that you write hello
world in C++. That's how big of a deal
this is. It used to be this. In fact,
even worse, this and I'm not going to
lie, the first time I saw this when I
was just teaching myself programming
back when I was 16 and young Cherno was
like, "Ooh, C++ like a low-level
language that games and game engines are
written in. I'm so interested in this.
Let me take a look at it." Oh,
why are they bitshifting the string into
what does count mean? By the way, if you
think that I'm making up the story
because why would a 16-year-old who's
just started learning programming know
what a bit shift operator is? It's
because the thing that got me into
programming in the first place was
writing a 3D renderer. And it's pretty
common to use bit operations in graphics
and rendering programming, such as to
separate out all the channels of a color
that's packed into an integer, for
example. So, yeah, true story. Anyway, I
took one long look at this monstrosity
and I was like, "Yeah, nah." And so from
the age of 16 to around the age of 19, I
didn't program in C++. I stuck with
Java. But then when I just turned 20, I
started working at EA and of course they
use C++. So I learned C++ and it became
my language of choice. That's right. It
took working at EA to get me to use C++.
And you know what? Somewhat anecdotally,
I'm going to go ahead and blame it on
this. I'm going to go ahead and blame
this on bit shifting strings into
couchs. But no more. A new breed of C++
developers is about to hit the market
because this monstrosity is finally
changing. Starting from C++ 23, which
sounds like a while ago because, you
know, C++ 23 corresponds with 2023 and
it's like 2025. But on the latest
version of Visual Studio, as of the 23rd
of June 2025, if we go into our project
and properties C, C++, and language, to
use C++ 23, you have to go past ISO C++
20 standard to the preview features from
the latest C++ working draft. So halfway
through 2025 in Visual Studio, MSVC,
pretty major compiler. Still does not
list C++ 23 as like its own thing. It's
just a it's preview. It's features from
the latest working draft, which by the
way, you will have to set to this if you
want to follow along with all the code
I'm going to write in this video. Well,
not all the code, not this. So yeah, I'm
not exactly 2 years late to the party
because the party is really just
beginning. And obviously if you are
working on any kind of major projects,
you will probably not be able to update
your C++ version in a while. That's
usually how it works, but that's a
different story. Anyway, as of C++ 23,
subject to your compiler and tool chain
and whatever else, you should be able to
include print instead of IO stream and
use this amazing function called std
print line. That's right, just like
Java, just like C. I mean C# has a right
line but anyway we have our we have a
print line function in C++
[Applause]
it's this is exciting this this is come
on I'm not playing this up for the
camera or YouTube this this is exciting
let me execute this program to show you
that this is in fact reality and not a
fantasy world
we did it there's going to be a time
where our current generation or older
generations are going to look at the new
generations of people and be like they
don't even know what this is. That no
one knows what this is. None of the none
of the kids know what this is. You know,
back in my day, we used to bit shift
left our strings into see outs. Sorry,
couts. It's going to be like floppy
discs. It's going to be like floppy
discs. You know what? Speaking of new
generation things and improvements to
current workflows and tools, let me
introduce Codeex, the sponsor of this
video. Codex is a really fun, intuitive
way to manage software projects,
particularly games. In fact, it's
actually made by game developers,
centralizing everything from
brainstorming to bug tracking and
community feedback. Put simply, it
offers what other generic tools can't. A
playful process to ship better games
that's faster and smoother for everyone.
It's unique and it's super fun to use.
It makes a whole project management into
a game itself. So, for example, here is
my Genesis 3D project. I'm remaking the
first game I ever made in 3D in Hazel.
I've got my hand. These are tasks that
I'm currently working on and that I want
to start working on soon. I've got all
of these different decks that signify
different areas of work that needs to be
done. And then there's another tab here
called timeline where I can basically
mark out various milestones of when I
want to get groups of tasks done. The
process is pretty simple. I can go into
like these decks, create various
different cards, fix that annoying bug,
save that card to my deck or directly to
my hand, give it various properties such
as effort required to actually complete
the task, various priorities. Once I put
it into my hand, I can hit play over
here to signify that I'm actually
working on that particular task. And
then when it's done, I can move it into
my done pile. And all of this is super
elegant, super fun to use. You can see
it really makes this whole process into
a card game. And there are so many more
cool features such as journeys which
kind of define the process of completing
tasks as well as integrations with
things like Discord and Steam for
community management. So go ahead and
check out Codeex using my link in
description below to make better games
in a better way. Huge thank you to
Codeex for sponsoring this video. Okay,
Cho. So did you really make a video all
about the fact that there's a new way to
write Hello World in C++?
Not quite. Because there's a lot more to
this than believe me this is a good
video. There's a lot more to this than
just this to the point that I would say
that logging is now much much much
better in C++ than it ever was before.
In fact, really this kind of started
with C++ 20 because C++ 20 introduced
this new thing called format std format
or standard format. What that allows you
to do is basically format a string in a
much more userfriendly or developer
friendly way. So for example, you can
write something like speed is and then
these curly brackets followed by a
parameter like 5.5F. You can put any
type you want into here and you don't
need to specify it in the actual string.
However, the type that you put in here
does actually need some kind of
definition that tells it how to convert
itself to a string because otherwise
this wouldn't exactly work. As you would
expect, all of the primitive types and
most of the kind of built-in types do
already support this conversion. But if
you're using like a class or a strruct
that you've written a custom type, then
of course you'll have to create an
implementation for this string
conversion. You can also write multiple
things like for example specifying
another parameter and you can use
whatever types you want over here and
the result of this format is an std
string. So this is basically the string
that we have created. I'll go ahead and
print it the old school way that our
elders will remember to show that this
is the only kind of modern functionality
we're using. And you can see our string
prints here correctly as you would
expect. Now, this itself is a fairly new
contribution to C++ being introduced in
C++ 20. And it really is like the
backbone for this whole new print
functionality. And this actually comes
from something called FMT. FMT is like a
formatting library that has been around
for a very long time and you can see FMT
print and FMT format. This has been
around for a very long time and the
author of this library is the one who
actually submitted the proposal to the
C++ committee to get this into the call
language. So, we have this guy to thank.
I actually don't know what his name is.
Anyway, thank you guy. And like this
library is good. It's really good. I've
been using it for years. Everyone's been
basically using this. That's why this
actually made it into the standard and
into the standard library. FMT is
actually what speed log uses for its
formatting. So speed log is a very very
good and popular fast C++ logging
library that I have been using since
like the very beginning of the game
engine series back in like 2018. And you
can see that it has featurerich
formatting using the excellent FMT
library. So, I've been using speed log
and then also FMT in Hazel since the
beginning for all of our logging and
string formatting needs. In fact, in
Hazel, if we go to log.h, which is the
header for all the logging stuff, you
can see that our macros here, they now
use scd format to actually format the
string. Because Hazel uses C++ 20, this
used to be FMT format. And then finally
this logger stuff that's going on over
here to actually log everything uses
speed log as you can see over here. So
slowly we are kind of moving from third
party libraries to just having this
stuff in the actual C++ standard library
which I think is great. So since std
format was introduced in C++ 20 std
print standard print I don't know I
don't really like saying standard
instead of std I just always end up
saying std because that's what's
written. I know it kind of stands for
standard, but maybe I should do a poll
or something. Anyway, I don't care. I'm
going to keep saying sd print in C++ 23.
There's actually two versions of this.
There's print and there's print line.
Print line is simply print with like a
new line character at the end as you
would expect. It basically does this.
So, if we have a look at the definition
here, you can see that it can take in
this format string. And then if we take
a look at the print implementation then
over here it's going to be using stdv
format which is just a variant of std
format which is kind of based off of
that fmt format library that we were
just talking about. So what that means
is back in our code we can just take
this and simply print this. We don't
need to first format our string and then
convert it to like an std string and
then send that into C out as would have
been the case in C++ 20. We can just do
std print line. Here is our string, our
format string which defines all of our
parameters and the actual I guess layout
of what gets printed as well as all of
the variables as arguments. We can run
this and there you go. There's the
result. If we have a look at
cppreerence.com
that of course has some more
information. You can see that all of
this stuff was introduced in C++ 23.
However, for some reason print line with
no arguments was only introduced in C++
26. So we're going to have to wait.
basically longer for that which is a
little bit annoying. And if you're
wondering what on earth print line with
no arguments would do, it would just
print a blank line. So if you want to
print a blank line, you still have to I
guess do std print with a new line
character in there. Or you could do see
out shift left sd end line or something,
but that will have other functionality
as well technically. Here it is valid
since C++ 26. Same effect as sdrint new
line. But what about custom types? What
if I want to make this work with like a
GLM vec 2 or I have my own strct over
here called point with X and Y. How do I
get that to easily print so that I don't
have to manually type out all of the
variables inside it? Well, you can use
this template specialization over here.
So, what we're doing is we're creating a
subclass of this class which has our
type over here and then we are adding
this function auto format. We're taking
in the actual variable. We're taking in
this format context and then you have to
make sure it's also const and it will
return this std formatter string format
with an sd format inside here and this
format context is taken in as an
argument. This is a little bit
confusing. It just has to be defined in
this particular way. If you get the
definition wrong, so like for example,
if I forget const and you try and
compile, there are several static
asserts inside this make format args
that will actually tell you what you're
doing wrong reasonably well as long as
you can like look up the standard. So
for example, if you forget the const
thing, it will tell you to make the
format usable, add const to format.
Otherwise, if you don't just don't have
a definition for that at all, it will
say that it cannot format an argument.
And to make t your custom type
formattable, provide a format T
specialization. And there's some
instructions over here inside the
standard. But if you don't forget const,
then over here in using this actual st
format, you can see I'm specifying how I
want my point to be printed and then I'm
adding it over here. I've just got a
basic point here, 28, and I'm printing
it here. Point is, and then that. And if
I run that, you can see that my point is
28. So, yeah, long story short, C++ now
kind of has like a logging
library/formatting library. Again,
really the bulk of this functionality is
due to SCD format, which has been around
since C++ 20. So most projects that
aren't huge scale corporate C++ projects
that are probably still on like C++ 03,
all of your projects should almost
definitely be on C++ 20 by now. So you
should still have std format even if you
don't have sd print line. But sd print
and sd print line just make this kind of
formatting a little bit easier because
now it's in the actual print function
rather than first having to use sedd
format getting a string from that and
then putting that into like print f or
into sdc see out or into your own
logging library. I kid you not when I
say that this is probably one of my
favorite additions to C++ 23. There are
some other good ones which I probably
will cover soon. In fact, maybe I should
just make a video talking about all the
new C++ 23 features now that it's
beginning to get some adoption. Let me
know if you want to see that in the
comment section below. But otherwise,
what do you think of this new print
functionality? Isn't it a big deal? I
mean, hello world has changed. Come on,
it's it's it's a big deal. I mean, SC
format is a bigger deal in my opinion.
That's actually a huge reason to jump up
to C++ 20. I don't know if this itself
is a reason for existing projects which
probably have their own logging
functionality to actually jump up to C++
23. However, I think I'm going to be
starting new projects with C++ 23 from
now on and just using these print
functions. Thank you guys for watching.
Don't forget to check out Codeex using
my link in description below and I will
see you next time. Goodbye.